<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="7B73D9ED-3021-4714-9A50-172338D8375F">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20110628" date="2011-06-28 14:20:47 -0700"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Mike McKerns</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>The nonlinear optical (NLO) responses of solutions of metallotexaphyrin (MTXP) complexes at 532 nm indicate that these materials have great promise as excited-state absorbing optical materials, although their full NLO characterization is only in its infancy. Degenerate four wave mixing (DFWM) experiments suggest that MTXP complexes have a predominantly electronic nonlinearity at 532 nm, and simulations of optical limiting (OL) measurements demonstrate reverse-saturable absorption (RSA) for MTXP complexes due to strong excited-state absorption (ESA) at 532 nm. For applications such as optical switches, it is desirable to design OL materials that exhibit strong RSA. However, material parameters such as absorption cross-section are wavelength-dependent; therefore, to fully understand the role of these parameters in the ESA and NLO response of MTXP complexes, measurements at a wide range of wavelengths must be performed. Most measurements of nonlinear response of MTXP complexes, however, have been performed at a single wavelength (532 nm) due in large part to the limitations of modern laser technology. To obtain a fluence strong enough to sufficiently characterize the NLO responses of solutions of MTXP complexes, a relatively strong laser such as an Nd:YAG must be used as the light source. The use of an Nd:YAG as a light source constrains the available wavelengths to 1064 nm, 532 nm, and harmonics thereof and, thus, only provides for a very slight set from which to draw conclusions. To allow for a more complete study of the NLO responses of MTXP complexes, a new, powerful, continuously tunable (over 0.85-1.05 &#xB5;m and harmonics thereof) laser system has been constructed utilizing LiF:F2+** color centers as the active medium.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Using the wavelength-dependency of excited-state absorption cross-sections to map the energy-level manifold for nonlinear optical materials.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>September 1, 2010</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-movie-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="1_Using_the_wavelength-dependency_of_excited-state_absorption_cross-sections_to_map_the_energy-level_manifold_for_nonlinear_optical_materials._files/sixlevelX2b.jpg" left="0px" top="0px" width="359px" height="269.25px"/>
</content>
