<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="7B73D9ED-3021-4714-9A50-172338D8375F">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20110628" date="2011-06-28 14:38:39 -0700"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Mike McKerns</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>The phonon density of states (DOS) originates with interatomic forces, and we have developed computational methods to extract the interatomic force constants from the measured inelastic scattering data, termed "Born-von Karman inversions." An added bonus of these procedures is their ability to correct experimental DOS curves for "neutron weighting," where phonon modes with large displacements of elements with big phonon cross-sections tend to be over-emphasized. A Born-von Karman model of lattice dynamics was developed for several metal alloys, where forces between atom pairs were represented by pairs of tensorial force constants that were optimized iteratively. Fits to experimental data were performed using the known neutron weightings of the elements, the instrument resolution function, and errors from experimental counting statistics. &#xD;&#xD;While the phonon entropy of solids is known to depend on chemical composition and structure at low temperatures, we have performed experiments to addresses the importance of electron-phonon interactions at higher temperatures. It is the free energy at elevated temperatures that is relevant for phase diagrams of most engineering materials. Temperature presents no new phenomena for configurational entropy, which depends only on atom configurations. The situation is more complicated for the vibrational entropy. From what we know so far, the phonon DOS usually changes with temperature, and usually these changes have thermodynamic importance. We also know, of course, that thermal expansion occurs because the interatomic potentials are not quadratic with atomic displacements. Larger lattice parameters weaken the interatomic forces, lower the vibrational frequencies, and increase the vibrational entropy. This increased vibrational entropy competes with an increased elastic energy of expansion in the free energy F = U &#x2013; TS. The minimum of F therefore occurs for a larger lattice parameter at higher temperatures. In addition to pure phonon excitations, electron-phonon interactions can also contribute to anharmonic behavior. For the thermal excitation of electron-phonon and phonon-phonon interactions, there is a naive expectation that their contributions to phonon anharmonicity will scale approximately as the Fermi temperature to the Debye temperature, minimizing the importance of electron-phonon interactions. This is not so clear for transition metals, however, where electron-phonon interactions cause Kohn anomalies. These two sources of anharmonicity, electron-phonon and phonon-phonon, are difficult to separate experimentally, and thermodynamic analyses usually group them together. We have performed Raman scattering measurements on several transition metal oxides at a series of elevated temperatures in order to better discern the origin of the phonon anharmonicity found in these materials.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Exploring the dependencies of electron-phonon interactions on temperature, pressure, and excited-state absorption in solid-state transition metal oxides.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>September 2, 2010</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-movie-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="2_Exploring_the_dependencies_of_electron-phonon_interactions_on_temperature,_pressure,_and_excited-state_absorption_in_solid-state_transition_metal_oxides._files/nla10bX2.jpg" left="0px" top="0px" width="362.6667px" height="272px"/>
</content>
