<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="02D80B19-D315-49C9-9F77-82755D44F001">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20110628" date="2011-06-28 14:20:58 -0700"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Mike McKerns</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>IDL is a dynamically typed language, similar to python, with the ability to create and manipulate variables at runtime. IDL has a scripting interface and an extensive library of scientific functions and visualization capabilities. IDL strives to enable the user to create meaningful visual representations of data in a minimal number of lines of code.&#xD;&#xD;While IDL provides a simple interactive data language and powerful graphics, it is not a natural environment for building large programs. IDL lacks several of numpy&#x2019;s capabilities for easily manipulating data arrays, and is also hindered by all variables sharing a single namespace. However, with pyIDL, IDL&#x2019;s large scientific library and advanced visualization capabilities are available from python. At the core, pyIDL provides the ability to seamlessly exchange variables and data objects between python and IDL. Also, pyIDL provides methods that can invoke IDL functions and procedures directly from python, and with python data objects. For users that are transitioning to python, pyIDL provides an &#x201C;interactive&#x201D; mode which yields direct access to the IDL scripting prompt.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>M. McKerns, &#x201C;pyIDL: python bindings to IDL&#x201D;, &lt;a href="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/projects/danse/pyIDL.html"&gt;http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/projects/danse/pyIDL.html&lt;/a&gt;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>July 30, 2010</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-movie-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="30_M._McKerns,_pyIDL__python_bindings_to_IDL,_http___www.cacr.caltech.edu_projects_danse_pyIDL.html_files/surf4.gif" left="0px" top="0px" width="345.0801px" height="305px"/>
</content>
