<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="02D80B19-D315-49C9-9F77-82755D44F001">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20110628" date="2011-06-28 14:20:57 -0700"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Mike McKerns</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>The DANSE project was prompted by the development of the Spallation Neutron Source (SNS) in Oak Ridge, Tennessee. Neutron scattering experiments performed at the SNS will produce data of unprecedented detail on the positions and motions of atoms and spins in materials, molecules, and condensed matter. The raw experimental data acquired with these instruments are not simple to interpret, and new software is required to transform the data into useful forms. Beyond such data reductions that are available today, there is an opportunity to interpret data using several major advances in computational materials science that have occurred over the past decade. The goals differ for each subfield of neutron science, but typically involve the fitting of experimental data to underlying physical models, simulations, or constraints imposed from other measurements. &#xD;&#xD;The exponential growth of computing power and resources enables increasingly complex simulations. A paradigm shift in software development is required -- the encapsulation of existing codes as independent &#x201C;engines&#x201D; interoperating in an integrated software environment is a more feasible approach for solving problems that require massively parallel architectures and large-scale distributed resources.  Similarly, the exploitation of new scientific opportunities provided by the higher quality data, and higher data acquisition rates, at the SNS requires the collaborative production of software on a scale unfamiliar to x-ray and neutron researchers.&#xD;&#xD;DANSE provides Monte Carlo neutron instrument simulations with robust sample material and sample container descriptions, where full direct simulation of neutron experiments are possible in DANSE by coupling the Monte Carlo sample to a materials theory engine. A robust global optimization framework enables existing forward models (i.e. engines) to be used in the prediction of materials and system parameters. The ability to quickly fit to experimental data allows for detailed pre-planning of experiments, or refining system or instrument parameters during the during the course of an experiment. Both increase the efficiency of a scientist&#x2019;s beam time, and lower the barrier to new science.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>B. Fultz, et al., &#x201C;DANSE: distributed data analysis for neutron scattering experiments&#x201D;, &lt;a href="http://danse.us"&gt;http://danse.us&lt;/a&gt;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>July 31, 2010</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-movie-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="31_B._Fultz,_et_al.,_DANSE__distributed_data_analysis_for_neutron_scattering_experiments,_http___danse.us_files/index.jpg" left="0px" top="0px" width="395.3117px" height="241.1591px"/>
</content>
