<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="02D80B19-D315-49C9-9F77-82755D44F001">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20110628" date="2011-06-28 14:20:56 -0700"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Mike McKerns</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Pyre is an integration framework for high performance computing. Written in Python, pyre is an extensible, object-oriented framework for specifying and staging complex, multi-physics simulations. Pyre provides developers of scientific computing software with a set of development tools, such as the &lt;a href="http://docs.danse.us/pyre/sphinx/pyreBasics.html#pyre-inventory"&gt;easy specification&lt;/a&gt; of user inputs for computing engines, &lt;a href="http://docs.danse.us/pyre/sphinx/pyreBasics.html#pyre-component"&gt;a decomposition scheme&lt;/a&gt; to construct sophisticated scientific software in a layered architecture, and a mechanism for &lt;a href="http://docs.danse.us/pyre/sphinx/pyreLibraries.html#journal"&gt;distributed debugging support&lt;/a&gt;. Pyre promotes intelligent software development by facilitating componentization, reusability, and the application of software design patterns.&#xD;&#xD;If a developer girdles their existing code in a thin framework layer, the code becomes a pyre &lt;i&gt;component&lt;/i&gt;, and is available for deployment in larger framework applications. Pyre manage the life-cycle and interactions of components in an elegant way, and removes the burden from the user in writing potentially fragile application infrastructure. By enforcing component interface specifications, pyre attempts to solve a very hard problem -- to make independently developed applications work together seamlessly. Because pyre components act as building blocks for larger applications, and pyre applications can be configured with simple key-value pairs, pyre developers benefit from much shorter concept-to-deployment costs.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>M.A.G. Aivazis, et al., &#x201C;pyre: an integration framework for high-performance computing&#x201D;, &lt;a href="http://danse.us/trac/pyre"&gt;http://danse.us/trac/pyre&lt;/a&gt;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>July 31, 2010</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-movie-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="31_M.A.G._Aivazis,_et_al.,_pyre__an_integration_framework_for_high-performance_computing,_http___danse.us_trac_pyre_files/pyre-logo-new.jpg" left="0px" top="0px" width="343.453px" height="103px"/>
</content>
