<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="02D80B19-D315-49C9-9F77-82755D44F001">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20110628" date="2011-06-28 14:20:56 -0700"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Mike McKerns</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>The ARCS spectrometer will advance the science of dynamical processes in materials. It is designed to measure excitations in materials and condensed matter having energies from a few meV to several hundred meV, with an efficiency better than any existing high-energy chopper spectrometer. ARCS is designed to enable research investigations of vibrational excitations and their relationship to phase diagrams and equations of state of materials, including materials with correlated electrons, and to measure spin correlations in magnets, superconductors, and materials close to metal-insulator transitions.&#xD;&#xD;The ARCS software primarily provides the ability to transform raw data from the instrument in the form of time-of-flight histograms into scattering intensity S(Q,E). This functionality is provided for both powder and isotropic scatterers. Monte Carlo simulations of the ARCS instrument are also available. Each individual neutron trajectory is calculated, from moderator to detector, and then the counts on the virtual detector can be compared against experiments. A neutron instrument is composed of several neutron components, or building blocks, thus greatly simplifying the reconfiguration of the instrument as required by the experiment. The majority of the neutron components available are based on the McStas package from Riso, with a few notable exceptions. A &#x201C;sample&#x201D; component is available, which can contain a number of different physical scatterers and scattering kernels. These scattering kernels inject materials physics into the instrument simulation, so that effects such as incoherent inelastic scattering and/or coherent inelastic scattering can be accurately simulated. More advanced kernels that support lattice dynamics and Heisenberg dynamics are also provided.</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>T. Kelley, M. McKerns, et al., &#x201C;ARCS: software for a wide angle-range chopper spectrometer at the SNS&#x201D;, &lt;a href="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/projects/ARCS/Software.html"&gt;http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/projects/ARCS/Software.html&lt;/a&gt;</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>July 31, 2010</richText>
  </textBox>
  <image id="generic-movie-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes" src="31_T._Kelley,_M._McKerns,_et_al.,_ARCS__software_for_a_wide_angle-range_chopper_spectrometer_at_the_SNS,_http___www.cacr.caltech.edu_projects_ARCS_Software.html_files/DANSE_roadmap2.jpg" left="0px" top="0px" width="442px" height="233.4804px"/>
</content>
