<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss xmlns:iweb="http://www.apple.com/iweb" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Research</title>
    <link>http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/~mmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research</link>
    <description>The focus of my research has been the coupling of theoretical, computational, and experimental approaches for the study of excited-state and energy materials. There are several challenges in the measurement and design of excited-state and energy materials -- the first of which is that experimental techniques are still very limited in the extent that they can measure structural or electronic changes resulting from the material being in an excited state. I have used excited-state absorption spectroscopy to study nonlinear optical materials, and have designed and built new lasers to extend nonlinear absorption spectroscopy to new wavelengths. Recently, I have expanded experimental techniques to Raman and neutron scattering, and have begun developing excited-state vibrational analogues for electronic time-resolved optical spectroscopy. As a theoretical compliment, I utilize quantum chemical methods in the calculation of excited-state materials properties, and work toward the full integration of quantum chemical calculations with both experiment simulations and experimental measurements. My ultimate goal is to develop a framework for the quantitative design of excited-state and energy materials.

Beyond the experimental challenges that exist, there are also difficulties that arise when computationally dealing with excited-state and energy materials. Multi-scale simulations are often required to provide an accurate calculation of bulk material properties for a selected molecular or crystallographic structure, and these calculations are often prohibitively expensive. Predictive calculations, such as a rigorous sensitivity analysis of materials design parameters, amount to a global optimization over design parameter space -- potentially requiring an already prohibitively large simulation to be performed hundreds, if not thousands, of times. Massively parallel, distributed, and asynchronously coupled computational methods must be developed to help minimize the computational time required to produce accurate predictions on the structure and properties of all but the simplest of excited-state and energy materials. I have developed an optimization framework, and also a framework for heterogeneous computing, that when utilized together, can make computationally intractable sensitivity and optimization problems much more tractable. Now, after a minimal amount of work required to bind a computational model to the optimization framework, we can begin to address parameter sensitivity, parameter correlation, and model validation issues for candidate materials models.</description>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing high-performance parallel and distributed computing in new algorithms for numerical optimization, parameter sensitivity, and design of experiments.</title>
      <link>http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/9/6_Utilizing_high-performance_parallel_and_distributed_computing_in_new_algorithms_for_numerical_optimization,_parameter_sensitivity,_and_design_of_experiments..html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cee1a683-9864-4fd0-8efe-5864ead9b420</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 6 Sep 2010 00:35:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <description>Key questions that scientists and engineers typically want to address can be formulated in terms of predictive science. Questions such as: &amp;quot;How well does my computational model represent reality?&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;What are the most important parameters in the problem?&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;What is the best next experiment to perform?&amp;quot; are fundamental in solving scientific problems. ``mystic`` is a framework for massively-parallel optimization and rigorous sensitivity analysis that enables these motivating questions to be addressed quantitatively as global optimization problems. Often realistic physics, engineering, and materials models may have hundreds of input parameters, hundreds of constraints, and may require execution times of seconds or longer. In more extreme cases, realistic models may be multi-scale, and require the use of high-performance computing clusters for their evaluation. Predictive calculations, formulated as a global optimization over a potential surface in design parameter space, may require an already prohibitively large simulation to be performed hundreds, if not thousands, of times. The need to prepare, schedule, and monitor thousands of model evaluations, and dynamically explore and analyze results, is a challenging problem that requires a software infrastructure capable of distributing and managing computations on large-scale heterogeneous resources.  We present the design behind an optimization framework, and also a framework for heterogeneous computing, that when utilized together, can make computationally intractable sensitivity and optimization problems much more tractable. The optimization framework provides global search algorithms that have been extended to parallel, where evaluations of the model can be distributed to appropriate large-scale resources, while the optimizer centrally manages their interactions and navigates the objective function.  New methods have been developed for imposing and solving constraints that aid in reducing the size and complexity of the optimization problem. Additionally, new algorithms have been developed that launch multiple optimizers in parallel, thus allowing highly efficient local search algorithms to provide fast global optimization. In this way, parallelism in optimization also can allow us to not only find global minima, but to simultaneously find all local minima and transition points -- thus providing a much more efficient means of mapping out a potential energy surface.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;M.M. McKerns, L. Strand, T. Sullivan, A. Fang, M.A.G. Aivazis, &#x201C;&lt;a href="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/~mmckerns/McKerns2011_proc_10th_scipy_conf.pdf"&gt;Building a framework for predictive science&lt;/a&gt;&#x201D;, Proceedings of the 10th Python in Science Conference, (submitted 2011).</description>
      <iweb:image href="Media/object002.jpg"></iweb:image>
      <iweb:comment link="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/9/6_Utilizing_high-performance_parallel_and_distributed_computing_in_new_algorithms_for_numerical_optimization,_parameter_sensitivity,_and_design_of_experiments..html#comment_layer" count="0" enabled="0"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the dependencies of electron-phonon interactions on temperature, pressure, and excited-state absorption in solid-state transition metal oxides.</title>
      <link>http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/9/2_Exploring_the_dependencies_of_electron-phonon_interactions_on_temperature,_pressure,_and_excited-state_absorption_in_solid-state_transition_metal_oxides..html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">ca93e85b-3870-4582-8e4d-e393f3e797e1</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 2 Sep 2010 23:33:28 -0700</pubDate>
      <description>The phonon density of states (DOS) originates with interatomic forces, and we have developed computational methods to extract the interatomic force constants from the measured inelastic scattering data, termed &amp;quot;Born-von Karman inversions.&amp;quot; An added bonus of these procedures is their ability to correct experimental DOS curves for &amp;quot;neutron weighting,&amp;quot; where phonon modes with large displacements of elements with big phonon cross-sections tend to be over-emphasized. A Born-von Karman model of lattice dynamics was developed for several metal alloys, where forces between atom pairs were represented by pairs of tensorial force constants that were optimized iteratively. Fits to experimental data were performed using the known neutron weightings of the elements, the instrument resolution function, and errors from experimental counting statistics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While the phonon entropy of solids is known to depend on chemical composition and structure at low temperatures, we have performed experiments to addresses the importance of electron-phonon interactions at higher temperatures. It is the free energy at elevated temperatures that is relevant for phase diagrams of most engineering materials. Temperature presents no new phenomena for configurational entropy, which depends only on atom configurations. The situation is more complicated for the vibrational entropy. From what we know so far, the phonon DOS usually changes with temperature, and usually these changes have thermodynamic importance. We also know, of course, that thermal expansion occurs because the interatomic potentials are not quadratic with atomic displacements. Larger lattice parameters weaken the interatomic forces, lower the vibrational frequencies, and increase the vibrational entropy. This increased vibrational entropy competes with an increased elastic energy of expansion in the free energy F = U &#x2013; TS. The minimum of F therefore occurs for a larger lattice parameter at higher temperatures. In addition to pure phonon excitations, electron-phonon interactions can also contribute to anharmonic behavior. For the thermal excitation of electron-phonon and phonon-phonon interactions, there is a naive expectation that their contributions to phonon anharmonicity will scale approximately as the Fermi temperature to the Debye temperature, minimizing the importance of electron-phonon interactions. This is not so clear for transition metals, however, where electron-phonon interactions cause Kohn anomalies. These two sources of anharmonicity, electron-phonon and phonon-phonon, are difficult to separate experimentally, and thermodynamic analyses usually group them together. We have performed Raman scattering measurements on several transition metal oxides at a series of elevated temperatures in order to better discern the origin of the phonon anharmonicity found in these materials.</description>
      <iweb:image href="Media/object064.jpg"></iweb:image>
      <iweb:comment link="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/9/2_Exploring_the_dependencies_of_electron-phonon_interactions_on_temperature,_pressure,_and_excited-state_absorption_in_solid-state_transition_metal_oxides..html#comment_layer" count="0" enabled="0"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using the wavelength-dependency of excited-state absorption cross-sections to map the energy-level manifold for nonlinear optical materials.</title>
      <link>http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/9/1_Using_the_wavelength-dependency_of_excited-state_absorption_cross-sections_to_map_the_energy-level_manifold_for_nonlinear_optical_materials..html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">ac10f47e-476d-4909-9ccd-ef313f4eafd0</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 Sep 2010 22:04:03 -0700</pubDate>
      <description>The nonlinear optical (NLO) responses of solutions of metallotexaphyrin (MTXP) complexes at 532 nm indicate that these materials have great promise as excited-state absorbing optical materials, although their full NLO characterization is only in its infancy. Degenerate four wave mixing (DFWM) experiments suggest that MTXP complexes have a predominantly electronic nonlinearity at 532 nm, and simulations of optical limiting (OL) measurements demonstrate reverse-saturable absorption (RSA) for MTXP complexes due to strong excited-state absorption (ESA) at 532 nm. For applications such as optical switches, it is desirable to design OL materials that exhibit strong RSA. However, material parameters such as absorption cross-section are wavelength-dependent; therefore, to fully understand the role of these parameters in the ESA and NLO response of MTXP complexes, measurements at a wide range of wavelengths must be performed. Most measurements of nonlinear response of MTXP complexes, however, have been performed at a single wavelength (532 nm) due in large part to the limitations of modern laser technology. To obtain a fluence strong enough to sufficiently characterize the NLO responses of solutions of MTXP complexes, a relatively strong laser such as an Nd:YAG must be used as the light source. The use of an Nd:YAG as a light source constrains the available wavelengths to 1064 nm, 532 nm, and harmonics thereof and, thus, only provides for a very slight set from which to draw conclusions. To allow for a more complete study of the NLO responses of MTXP complexes, a new, powerful, continuously tunable (over 0.85-1.05 &#xB5;m and harmonics thereof) laser system has been constructed utilizing LiF:F2+** color centers as the active medium.</description>
      <iweb:image href="Media/object000.jpg"></iweb:image>
      <iweb:comment link="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/9/1_Using_the_wavelength-dependency_of_excited-state_absorption_cross-sections_to_map_the_energy-level_manifold_for_nonlinear_optical_materials..html#comment_layer" count="0" enabled="0"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlating structure and bond character to electronic hyperpolarizability and spectral response of conjugated organic molecules.</title>
      <link>http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/8/31_Correlating_structure_and_bond_character_to_electronic_hyperpolarizability_and_spectral_response_of_conjugated_organic_molecules..html</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">6c5877ae-e1cf-4e25-8223-77cd5b2382d8</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 23:33:20 -0700</pubDate>
      <description>To a great extent, the structure-property relations for the linear polarizability and hyperpolarizabilities have been treated separately and as mostly unrelated. However, Gorman and Marder have recently shown that &#x3B1;, &#x3B2;, and &#x3B3; of &#x3C0;-electron conjugated chain molecules can be correlated with the chemically relevant parameter bond length alternation (BLA), &#x3C0;-electron conjugated bond order alternation, or bridged-atomic charge sum (BACS). We will use quinoid-aromatic character (QAC), which provides a measure of the deviation from resonance bond length. By treating conjugated organic molecules as a mixture of two limiting resonance structures, one of which is neutral and the other of which exhibits a high degree of charge separation, it is possible to determine the molecular structure and, consequently, the polarizability of a molecule by examining the relative energetics of the two forms. The charge separated form can be stabilized by a combination of tuning the Coulomb potential of the end groups (i.e. the donor/acceptor strength), modifying the molecular topology (i.e. gain of aromatic charge stabilization energy upon charge separation), and changing the solvent-mediated polarization (i.e. more polar solvents stabilizing charge separation). Each of these forces has different local effects on the molecular and electronic structures; however, to a first-order approximation, these forces all correspond to an application of an effective electric field across a &#x3C0;-conjugated system. The effective field induces a charge separation and, thus, provides for a new equilibrium geometry and electronic configuration. This treatment allows the derivative relations, among static &#x3B1;, &#x3B2;, and &#x3B3; (i.e. &#x3B1;(1), &#x3B1;(2), and &#x3B1;(3)) and the electric field E to be rewritten as a function of static electric perturbing field F, where the derivatives with respect to F are evaluated at the new equilibrium geometry.</description>
      <iweb:image href="Media/object001.jpg"></iweb:image>
      <iweb:comment link="http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/%7Emmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research/Entries/2010/8/31_Correlating_structure_and_bond_character_to_electronic_hyperpolarizability_and_spectral_response_of_conjugated_organic_molecules..html#comment_layer" count="0" enabled="0"></iweb:comment>
    </item>
    <iweb:dateFormat>MMMM d, yyyy</iweb:dateFormat>
    <iweb:baseURL>http://www.cacr.caltech.edu/~mmckerns/Mike_McKerns/Research</iweb:baseURL>
    <iweb:maximumSummaryItems>10</iweb:maximumSummaryItems>
  </channel>
</rss>
